<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Fluid Mechanics]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Fluid Mechanics</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 07:51:33 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 07:51:30 GMT</pubDate><copyright><![CDATA[graphegg]]></copyright><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator>graphegg</dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[gibbs free energy]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:thermo" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#thermo</a> 
 <br><a href=".?query=tag:thermo" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener">#thermo</a><br>
BAD TITLE, it has a lot more than GFE<br>
This gives maximum possible work that can be extracted from a process<br>
Gibbs energy requires isothermal conditions<br> T_o is the ambient temperature, matter of notation use 300K<br>Note

<br>or<br>
<br>or<br>
<br>
B,X and G are just different ways of looking at systems, you can use anything even U and S to evaluate stuff
<br>thus<br>
=&gt; =&gt; =&gt;=&gt; =&gt;=&gt; =&gt; =&gt; =&gt; =&gt; <br><br>PV = RT<br>
<br><br>integrating,<br><br>Alpha is the coefficient of thermal expansion (volumetric)<br>Problem
water from 30 to 50 degrees celsius, 1 to 100 bar<br>
to get enthalpy change, we take the above equation at constant pressure to 50 degrees celsius then at constant temp from 1 to 100 bar
<br><br>Problem
We have a process, a secret process in which air comes in at 2kg/s, 20C, 4bar. 1kg/s comes out at 60C, 1 bar, 1 kg comes out at -20C, 1 bar. Is this process possible?
<br><br>Let S for stream 1 be 0<br>
ITS FEASIBLE<br>
LOL<br>Problem
Do exergy balance. Heat exchanger with 4 streams. One of liquid stuff with  coming in at .inlet and outlet are 150 and 60C. The other of cooling water between 40 and 30C
<br><br>How much cooling water needed?<br>
the exergy difference between liquid stuff:<br>
The exergy balance for the water<br>
exergy total balance<br>
<br>
<br>
Note - I did out-in not in-out so the signs are a bit odd. Rest assured thermodynamics hasnt failed us
<br>
NOTE NUMBER 2 - SINCE ENTHALPY BALANCE EXISTS, THE H PART OF X CANCELS OUT CUS NET H IS 0, SO IT ENDS UP BEING T_NAUGHT (DELTA S) EPIK EPIK EPIK
<br><br><br>imagine we are compressing air from 30C, 1 bar to 10 bar pressure unknown temp<br>
we need multistage compressors because no material on earth can handle a temperature difference of more than probably 100 or 200 (not metal and can be used on the oaring of a compressor to have 0 tolerance)<br>in multistage compressors we need compression ratios that are equal between all the compressors so the work done is minimized (this is left as an exercise for myself) - easy shit<br>Problem
we got a pump, we got a box, we try to take out air from box isothermally until vacuum from 1 bar
<br><br>What is enthalpy of the system at start?<br>
its H=U+PV<br>
=&gt; <br>
=&gt;712  300  1.157+10^5]]></description><link>gibbs free energy.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">gibbs free energy.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[graphegg]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 06:49:53 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>